He said that he didn't want me in the possession of any firearms while I'm in the possession of the bomb and I'm taking it.
Why is that?
Because I don't want any arrests.
Do we want terrorist and criminal organizations to be understood?
Yes,
we do.
How are we going to do that?
Quite often that's going to involve human sources.
The RCMP has a long history of using undercover agents in order to keep closer tabs on anyone they feel they need to.
Everybody knows about the ordinary police and they see them every day,
but most people don't encounter the political police,
but politics in a liberal democracy is police.
Since the very beginning of the Canadian Confederation,
the political police and the secret services are monitoring,
trying to criminalize and even sabotage groups of racialized minorities and the social movements that disturb the status quo.
Canada over the years has been very quiet about the things that it has done wrong,
all of the rights that it's breached,
and so the rest of the world really doesn't understand just how problematic Canada's national security and domestic terrorism activities actually are.
You've put all of these resources into counterterrorism,
but what happens if there aren't a lot of terrorists out there?
What if the threat is actually fairly small?
What are these people going to do?
Since the onset of the war on terror,
we have seen how the majority of these terrorism prosecutions have relied on incitement by informants,
including the targeting of individuals who are vulnerable and targeted because they were vulnerable.
The Kharodi and Natal case is the most prominent instance of this.
BC Supreme Court judge describes as egregious conduct by the RCMP.
This in the case of the couple who planted bombs at the British Columbia legislature three years ago.
Without the deceit,
threats and encouragement of police,
that plot would never have been carried out.
I was played around by the cops and they lied and manipulated me and
I ended up doing just over three years in jail.
This is an inside false flag job perpetrated by the Canadian government and they're using us.
The police took virtually all of the meaningful and necessary steps to go from A to B,
from idea to construction to...
Planting.
If part of the response to global warming is for the Aboriginal communities to step up and say,
not on our land,
this needs to be corrected.
The problem is what's happened in the Nuttall case becomes a blueprint.
For how you can deal with Aboriginal communities by planting agent provocateurs to undermine some of those movements and undermine the right to free speech and the ability to step up for something as critical as global warming.
I was living in Surrey with my husband Omar.
One day he went out to the gas station where we always got our coffee and there was a man there who claimed he was a Muslim and said that he was looking after his brother's daughter and she had run away.
And he needed help finding her.
And Omar immediately said,
sure,
I'll take you to where all the young kids hang out and show you all the places around here where she might be.
And obviously this was a completely contrived story.
There was no niece.
This was a police officer trying to infiltrate us.
He took them out for coffee after they looked around.
And from then on he said,
you know,
as new converts,
I want to help you.
He taught us how to pray and he gave us prayer mats.
Hey brother,
get some groceries.
Take care of your wife,
okay?
Or do whatever you want with them.
Pretty much every time we saw him,
he gave us money.
And we were in abject poverty at the time.
Like,
we were pretty much eating,
like,
a pack of ramen noodles a day,
and that was all we could afford to eat.
We became Muslims,
I think,
in 2011.
We said the Shahada,
but we didn't really understand what it meant.
I don't think at that point I'd even finished reading the whole Quran,
you know.
I certainly didn't know how to pray.
We decided to convert when we were living on the street.
We went into a store one day because Omar needed new boots.
And they had on the counter a book called The Key to Understanding Islam.
And I just asked,
how much does this book cost?
And he said,
take it,
they're free.
And we went back to where we were sleeping with a group of other street kids that night.
We felt something when we read that book,
that we were on to the truth.
I got a phone call out of the blue from this so-called brother from the mass jeep who turned out to be Mr.
X.
We became fast friends.
He would come over to my house,
you know,
and spend 10 hours a day.
It's true,
Abdul,
he did teach us how to pray a little bit,
and he taught us some of the Quran,
but the majority of the religion was taught to me by this Mr.
X and another person who...
Was not mentioned in court,
but who also had befriended me,
and he taught me a lot about the dean as well.
I found out later from my lawyer that he was in fact a CSIS agent as well.
So there was two of them,
and when one wasn't there,
the other one was.
If we refer to the law,
the main mission of the SCRS is to inform the Government of Canada on national security threats.
And to do that,
the SCRS will infiltrate groups and sometimes even radicalize them.
He showed us a lot of videos about
Muslims being tortured and killed in various countries.
Pretty much,
in retrospect,
it was very obvious that he was trying to radicalize us.
But at the time,
we were just like,
oh my God,
all this horrible stuff is going on.
It's not that we thought we could do anything about it,
but we were horrified by it.
We were doing our best to learn about the religion,
and we were going at our own pace,
and then all of a sudden,
we were spending 10 hours a day with these people every day,
you know,
having this crap shoved down our throats.
Agent X suggested that we should plant bombs in a shopping mall.
And I was like,
wow.
Pourquoi radicaliser les groupes?
Eh bien,
après ça,
le SCRS peut arriver et dire,
vous voyez à quel point que le monde est rempli de menaces.
What I mean is,
you see how much we need an organization like us,
the SRS.
So,
in other words,
the SRS justifies its own existence by radicalizing groups and trying to show them as being more dangerous than they were at the beginning.
These two guys,
they worked with me for about two years before handing me over to the RCMP.
That's kind of how the whole thing started was with this Mr.
X and then this cop who pretended to have a missing niece.
RCMP were tipped off about the plot by the Canadian Security Intelligence Service and back in February began Project Souvenir,
an integrated covert operation.
It all traced back to the way this thing started and some of the early interactions the police had with Mr.
Nuttall,
including attending to his residence,
speaking with him because there was a report he was speaking very loudly into the phone about jihad and all kinds of things,
and so the police attend to his...
their basement suite and have an interaction with him and decide that maybe they should get the psychiatric nurse.
There's essentially a psychiatric nurse on duty who's there to assess,
sort of give at least a preliminary assessment on folks.
And that's one of the events that sort of before this operation.
In relation to Nuttall and Karodi,
you would say that was a troubling set of statements.
We have reason to be concerned here.
And then you see,
from reason to be concerned,
to the outcome of that,
a huge trajectory of,
no,
you never thought?
No,
wait a minute.
obviously not.
What are you doing?
Oh my God.
Right?
You go down that trajectory,
and you say,
what the f***?
What happened there?
He just kind of put it on me,
you know?
That's what I don't want.
I don't want to put on you something,
brother.
To just come up with a plan all of a sudden.
No.
Very early on he was always pressuring us to come up with a plan.
And I don't remember exactly when it started,
but it was definitely an ever-present.
Push of him to always come up with a plan,
come up with a plan.
He was always pushing us and pushing us and pushing us to make these plans that we didn't feel we were capable of,
nor did we have any real desire to make any sort of jihadist plans.
The agents of the infiltration will collect information.
In some cases,
they will break the law.
the infiltration agents will become the leaders of the organizations they started to infiltrate.
And in the most extreme cases,
they will provoke the police,
that is to say,
they will put the maximum pressure on people so that they become a terrorist threat,
as in the case of the Souvenir Project.
I need spiritual guidance from somebody.
If you need spiritual guidance,
text me what you need.
That's not,
text it to me,
I'll try to find you the answer.
I need a brother I can talk to about these things.
You can talk to me brother.
I know and I love talking to you about it.
You can talk to me.
You're the only one that I know in this whole dunya,
other than my wife,
that I...
He understands what I'm going through.
I was told not to ever go to the mosque or talk to anyone.
I begged him.
I said,
I need to speak to an imam.
Do you have a spiritual advisor or anybody?
I was having doubts,
spiritual doubts.
He said,
you're not going to speak to an imam.
You can direct your questions to me.
Our path is predetermined by Allah.
Allah chooses it for us.
We don't choose it for ourselves.
He told us things like predestination is everything.
There's no such thing as free will.
And everything is already decided.
And these people are meant to die.
And there's nothing that you can do that's your own choice.
That's not the truth about Islam.
there's
belief in predestination,
but there's also human free will.
And he completely neglected to tell us that part.
Everything is in the hand of God.
How do I say it again?
Kulshi fi yadi Allah.
Kulshi fi di Allah.
Fadi Allah.
Muslim
RCMP officers were deliberately used in order to
to parade as religious authorities in order to increase the coercive effect by telling Kharodi and Natal that this was something that was religiously recommended or a religious obligation for them.
We were so caught up with this guy.
He was giving us money,
he was buying us groceries,
he was
Pretty much like a godsend to us.
And so we believed everything that he said.
And so we didn't go to mosques because he told us that we wouldn't learn anything there.
You understand,
trust me for once.
I'm doing this because I want to help you.
I see you really want it,
I want to help you.
And the other thing,
we passed.
The return point here,
we passed it.
That's it.
He said he fought jihad multiple times,
you know,
and told me what it felt like to kill.
The fact that he could get me any weapon I needed to get the job done,
including,
you know,
rocket launchers and machine guns and the like,
all I needed to do was make one phone call and it would be done.
Here we had the officers making it clear that they had engaged in prior terrorist acts.
There isn't a prohibition against that.
It's not a bar.
But the courts,
of course,
have cautioned against that.
The dangers are obvious that when you do that,
you run the risk of potentially creating a situation that is abusive,
one that...
...potentially leads to involuntary or questionable confessions.
How much explosive do you need?
As much as I can get.
I want to make as many rockets as I can get.
I want to have enough missiles that I can fill an entire box of a band.
You're putting on an act to impress them so that they think you're hardcore.
And they're putting on an act.
and you don't know that they're putting on an act.
So,
neither you or the cops know that you're all acting in the Truman Show in a movie starring you with the main goal of putting you behind bars for the rest of your life.
We're up here,
right?
So we're gonna come down here,
down quadra,
and turn right.
Here,
let me take a picture of you.
They go on what they refer to as the recce,
which is a shorthand for reconnaissance.
And off they went over to Victoria
May 24th,
25th in 2013.
I guess these are like the founding fathers or something,
like...
The plan was to scope out locations as much as there was a plan.
Say cheese.
Mr.
Nuttall at one point had mentioned Victoria as a potential spot.
And the police liked that one because that was a target that they knew they could control.
And of course,
months later,
that's where they ended up directing them to go.
Based on the extreme effort that was injected into coercing this mentally vulnerable couple into participating in a bomb plot.
It seems very clear that there is a deep investment in projecting an image of a Muslim,
quote-unquote,
terrorist threat.
We were very much still in the learning phase of becoming Muslims.
I think that that has a lot to do with why we were targeted,
because someone who had been Muslim longer and who knew more about the faith.
Would be a lot harder to manipulate.
There is endless back and forth on this notion about whether or not racial and religious and political profiling is part of what goes on.
The security services will tell you no in the same way that the police will tell you no.
That's not what we're doing.
We may take it into account as a factor,
but we're not profiling.
There is no sense in communities that are targeted that there's any credence to the denial.
There are targeted communities.
It's very clear.
One of the recurrent themes that goes way back into the origins of Canada,
right up to the present,
is that national security threats have created suspect communities.
Maybe ideological communities as they were during the Cold War.
They may be religious or ethnic communities as they are in the war on terror.
You see a threat emanating from...
Some community,
at least people that claim to speak for that community or come out of that community,
who may not represent anything other than a very small,
you know,
tiny proportion of that community,
but the suspicion is spread over the community as a whole.
Since 9-11,
Muslims have been subject to targeting suspicion.
mass surveillance in our homes,
in our places of worship,
in our communities,
for violence that has never happened at all,
simply on the basis of a projected threat of violence.
There's lots of focus on so-called Islamist violence,
but actually the far right,
at least when it comes to lone-actor terrorism,
have killed many more people over the last few decades,
and yet what gets more attention from the security side is focus on
Islamism as opposed to a far-right racist sort of violence.
We have a situation where
98% of completed terrorism prosecutions in Canada have been of Muslims or people linked to Muslim groups,
even though less than 10%
of deaths from mass political violence in Canada since 9-11 has been caused by Muslims.
And we note that Muslims accused of terrorism,
Muslims prosecuted for terrorism,
when they are incarcerated,
they have been subject to some of the harshest regimes of incarceration,
even though in none of these cases has there ever been actually any violence committed.
And in fact,
in many of these cases,
the thwarted plots were the product of a great deal of intervention by state informants and Asian provocateurs.
You guys were really trying to set me up.
You would just give me a fake bomb and tell me to go bomb a target and the bomb wouldn't go off and then I would be grabbed.
Okay?
So,
this is the wisdom of my wife.
She told me this.
Okay?
Just before I came to see you.
I suspected it could be police and it could have been a set up.
So how can I go to the authorities if they're the ones planning this false flag attack?
You know what I mean?
I can't go to them.
To prove you my real intent?
Yeah.
That's what you want?
Sorry,
Ash.
You can't do that.
I'm not going to.
No,
it's not that I can't do that.
But just for that,
I'm not going to do it,
Ashley.
If we cannot trust each other,
I don't think,
because what we're going to,
it's more important than trust.
If we don't have the trust,
we don't have it,
Ashley.
With the gun or not,
we don't have it.
Okay,
I'm going to trust you,
brother.
The infiltration agents will be ready to say absolutely anything,
to do anything to protect their cover,
to continue to convince the targeted person that they are one of theirs.
But the problem is when the police are mistaken for targets.
like
Omar Natal.
If they manage to look like real terrorists,
they will terrorize their target.
Like I told you,
any time,
any day,
if you say,
you know what,
I still have some doubt.
I cannot go through with this.
I hear the door.
Like,
we're going to be brothers.
We're brothers for life.
You're giving me a way out.
but you're telling me that we've passed the point of no return.
So in my mind,
I'm thinking this way out is a test.
He's testing us to see if we will back out and to see if we're true Muslims and we're going to go through with it.
And if we back out,
well then they're just gonna shoot us in the head and be done with this,
you know what I mean?
I have a panic anxiety disorder and I take tranquilizers for it.
I was just so caught up in that that I didn't even really stop to think that there might be an easier way out.
I thought that the only way out would be to either go through with it or to commit suicide.
And suicides go to hell in the Islamic religion,
so I wasn't going to do that.
We would leave it until the absolute last minute when I came to meet with him and he'd be like,
okay,
what's your plan?
It's a Samud rocket.
You just put it up on a launcher and then you hit the fuse and it goes flying off.
I had a million plans,
but I had no real plan.
They're all just off the cuff,
like,
what if we do this?
You know?
Which just angered him further,
you know.
We didn't know what to do,
but we were starting to get scared that if we didn't come up with some kind of plan that we would be harmed.
Because now we knew him,
we knew that he was a mujahid,
and if we didn't...
Do what he wanted us to do.
We thought that he would find a way to eliminate us.
Okay,
so here's a little diagram.
Perker cooker?
Yeah,
that's what they used in the Boston bombings.
That's the same bomb they used.
And I figure,
heck,
it worked for them,
but...
It can work for us.
I want to just use it as a tester,
to test it before I go to the trouble of making the real thing,
you know?
When the pressure cooker bomb happened to get mentioned,
based on events in Boston,
they seized on that and continued to come back to that in all their discussions.
I told him about what you told me last time.
Yeah,
yeah.
He said that's a great idea.
The amount of discrimination,
particularly against visible minorities,
but most particularly against Muslims,
at least in a national security and intelligence context,
is rampant within the organizations.
Not just with respect to the targets,
but with respect to the actual agents themselves that are doing the work.
There is an internal discrimination and bias built into the system.
one of the themes that plays out in
every one of the cases that I've touched where there's been harassment is the people that are in these organizations,
in particular CESIS,
when they come from minority communities,
in particular the Muslim community,
their chance at any level of promotion within that organization historically has been zero.
They operate behind walls of great secrecy,
but what we have heard from the reports of whistleblowers,
who are still,
by the way,
not protected in legislation from retribution,
are acts of Islamophobia,
racism and homophobia that we would otherwise think would be the purview of the far right.
A complaint by five former CSIS employees said that in the office there were posters with the pictures of the World Trade
Center towers burning.
with the words 99 names of Allah inscribed on them.
A
CISIS employee who wore hijab reported having to take a polygraph examination about how many times per day she prayed and who she associated with in the community.
These rare glimpses that we get behind these walls of secrecy that have been erected to protect national security practices show a culture of racism.
Think about today's Royal Canadian Mounted Police,
the RCMP.
They were created or born out of the European desire to appropriate Indigenous lands and resources and force settlement and take over our very lucrative trade networks.
So they were the enforcers of effectively not just colonization.
but what we now know as genocide,
genocidal laws,
policies,
practices,
by state officials and by law enforcement.
One of the reasons why the Mounted Police are created,
they're created to basically ethnically cleanse the
Canadian plains,
to move these people off so
Euro-Canadian settlement can occur.
They were originally the Northwest Mountain Police,
and their whole role was to remove Indigenous peoples from specific territories for the purposes of settlement or railroads or resource extraction.
Right down to the creation of the Mounties,
that's what it's for,
specifically to control Indigenous people,
to protect the economic gain of the country.
And I think that economic piece is really important.
We see that even now with things like In Wet'suwet'en and with Ferry Creek.
Part of that is coming from the drive of these businesses who,
you know,
want to be able to lay pipelines,
want to be able to take down the trees they want to take down.
So the Mounties are still doing that nearly 150 years later.
They manufactured us as a dangerous threat in the very beginning,
and they've continued to maintain us as a threat.
You know,
we went from dangerous savages to now we're terrorists.
And they've done that to multiple other groups.
So people who think that it can't happen to them,
it happened to Indigenous peoples,
now it's happening to other groups like Muslims and Asians.
Anybody who challenges the current power and structure and wealth system,
they've manufactured into a threat to maintain the status quo.
June 16-18,
2013,
they take him to Kelowna.
They needed to get them out of their residence so that they could insert a listening device.
I told you,
I knew you'd give me a gumsy-pussy.
We're so happy to see you,
brother.
He's happy you're right.
You want him here,
I brought him here.
There was a second undercover officer who was there,
who they had met at the wreck.
back in May in Victoria.
They were fond of him.
I'm really excited because it's something that can work for sure.
It's feasible,
it's very realistic.
So
I was glad to see that you were starting to think,
you know,
starting to think about that,
you know.
And it was sort of he and the primary undercover back and forth,
pushing this pressure cooker plan,
saying the rockets were not feasible.
You know,
that they needed to get funding from those above them,
and that wasn't going to happen unless it was for that plan.
And it goes over,
well,
the whole trip up to Kelowna over a number of days.
However,
we saw a few mistakes.
He put us up in this hotel room,
and we had one hotel room,
and he's like,
this one is just for you to relax,
but this hotel room is where you work on your plan.
Now,
are you going with the pressure cooker after the collection?
I believe that that's what Ali said to do.
And I trust him and I trust you and we seem to trust him.
Yeah,
so...
After the Kelowna trip,
it was a bit of a snowball in terms of,
well,
that was the plan.
There were some back and he'd have moments where he was back to rockets or decided he needed to do something else.
But it became almost inevitability after that.
Come on and push.
We often hear the claim that the way to counter racism in national security agencies is to diversify them,
to multiculturalize them,
to make sure that we have more representations from Muslims and others.
But what we see in cases like Karodi and Natal is that,
to the contrary,
the presence of Muslim officers is used to further extend the arm of securitization and the reach of these agencies.
into vulnerable Muslim communities and families.
And so far from being a solution to racism,
diversification of these institutions of violence is in fact an exacerbation of racism.
The Mounties started out as a very white Anglo-Saxon force.
Like,
this was not for anybody else.
And they had this uncomfortable realization,
you know,
around World War I that...
It's really hard for white people to infiltrate people who are not white and get away with that successfully.
And that's when they actually first started to hire people who weren't Anglo-Saxon,
who didn't have that sort of specific build and look that the RCMP was used to.
They were looking for people who actually understood various different Eastern European languages.
In the late 19th century,
early 20th century in Canada,
several expatriate communities were targeted by the Canadian state,
were the object of surveillance and infiltration,
simply because there were people...
among these communities who continued in
Canada the fight against colonialism in their native country.
There are very well documented cases in the Irish immigrant community and the Sikh community,
and it has happened in several other communities,
cases that are less well documented.
When the so-called modern RCMP comes into existence at the end of the First World War,
all they're doing in that period is more sort of surveillance security.
They don't have an ordinary crime-fighting role that we associate maybe with them today.
Most major moments in history with the RCMP,
from the Winnipeg general strike,
the Regina riot,
there are Mounties there who are infiltrating,
who are part of it.
In the
1920s, the Ku Klux Klan is heavily active in Canada,
especially in Western Canada,
especially in
Saskatchewan. There are thousands of members,
it's influencing the political system.
The RCMP takes notice of it,
but in terms of the resources and the extent of the surveillance,
it's just not anything on the same level as that's done to a threat on the left.
The main threat,
the main focus,
is on the Communist Party of Canada.
All the more so we are coming,
unions and big talk.
In the interwar years,
communists were involved politically and in the trade unions.
And from the time of the Russian Revolution on,
they had pride of place as the preeminent threat to the security of Canada.
The Mounties were so hyper-fixated on communists that they didn't really pay attention to the fact that they were a part of the security of Canada.
much attention to Nazis in like the
1930s throughout Canada.
You know,
there wasn't a lot of attention to that.
Thank you.
So the Cold War was a kind of self-perpetuating machine that created fear and suspicion and led to the massive infiltration by state agents and sources that they developed of a whole series of institutions
of civil society.
The police and the secret services have monitored many social movements.
We're talking about workers'
struggles,
unemployment,
student movements,
racialized minorities who are organizing against colonialism.
In fact,
everything that was a little too left-wing,
to the taste of the Canadian state,
became a target for agents of infiltration.
The McDonald Commission in the early
1980s came up with the number that they had amassed files on
800,000 individuals and groups.
When the McDonald Commission came out,
the government sat on it for six months.
and released it with two of their own commissioned reports that directly contradicted the results of the five-year inquiry.
A lot of stuff gets jammed into those extensive reports that the public never really seems to grapple with,
and the RCMP and the federal government never is actually sort of,
seems to be forced to sort of stand there and say,
yeah,
we did this,
we're doing this differently,
like there's always,
there's a lot of politics and you can sort of dodge.
Suddenly in 1989,
the Berlin Wall comes down.
A year or two later,
the Soviet Union collapses.
The whole enemy they'd been fixated on since 1917 vanished,
almost.
And then,
of course,
in September the 11th,
2001,
you had the attack on New York and the Twin Towers,
and suddenly the Cold War was reconceived,
just changed.
the names,
changed the,
you know,
a few of the,
but now it was
Islamic extremism and in a time in which there were enormous technological changes that were going on in terms of how you would actually carry out the political policing and the national security in terms of the toolbox of surveillance that was increasing by leaps and bounds.
I plan to make a video of saying,
you know,
I've,
I,
we did this because you're one of nine countries to turn your back on Palestine and you've been doing it ever since and we know you're in bed with the Zionists.
He had a brother from
France show up,
you know,
and he brought over the black ISIS flag.
As-salamu alaykum wa rahmatullahi wa barakatuh,
brothers and sisters.
My name is Yahya,
and this is my wife,
Miriam.
And we are a new Muslim Congress.
People think that was our flag.
It wasn't.
It was the cops'
flag.
They brought it.
They're the ones filming it.
And it was the French guy who they said was in charge of their multimedia department.
If we don't help ourselves,
then
Allah helps those who help themselves.
This government is fully committed to protecting both our freedoms and our security,
both of which are under attack from the group ISIS.
The threat we face today is not CSIS,
it is ISIS.
Certainly the government had stepped up the rhetoric.
and stepped up the actions around enforcement of national security.
Stephen Harper had made public statements about this
ISIS, the Islamic State being this great evil that has descended upon us.
And there presumably were some pressures that were being felt by the agencies to come up with results.
If you want proof that the worldwide jihadist movement has declared war on Canada,
look no further than the Nuttall-Carroti case.
So he used that as an excuse to push Bill C-51 through.
like Bill C-51 or Bill C-59,
which is the subsequent
National Security Act that was instituted by the Liberals,
they end up retroactively legalizing illegal practices that security agencies were engaging in.
So,
for example,
courts and journalistic investigations found that CSIS was impermissibly engaging in mass surveillance and retention of data of Canadians,
and so the law then goes and retroactively legalizes that.
In the C-51,
they basically said that CSIS could break the law,
they could violate charter rights.
There was an outer limit that was established,
but that outer limit is quite amazing.
Basically,
it couldn't involve murder,
rape,
or impeding the criminal process.
But anything short of that?
Okay.
Just about everything on the list of what they're allowed to do in their threat reduction is illegal.
Certainly,
if I did it,
it would be illegal.
And so that whole raft of messing with somebody's communication,
messing with their movements,
taking something out of their possession,
and they can also...
break and enter or do anything that they need to do in order to do the thing that they're trying to do.
And there would be a secret warrant given by a judge and no post-action accountability and no knowledge,
in fact,
on the part of anybody else that such warrants had been granted.
In 2015,
the Parliament came with the C-51 bill.
Two years later,
the Canadian Parliament adopted the C-59 bill,
which adds other exceptions to criminal offences that the SCRS is not allowed to commit.
So,
from now on,
the Parliament says to the SCRS that it is not allowed to arrest a person,
that it is not allowed to torture a person,
that it is not allowed to cause damage to goods when it can affect the safety of a person.
It's still revealing to see that the Parliament judged that it was necessary to tell the Canadian Secret Service that they cannot torture citizens.
They continue to surpass what their legal authorities are and we don't have a say.
At best,
they make submissions before a judge in camera,
but there's no Indigenous representative,
there's no human rights ombudsperson or anyone there or legal expert to provide counter.
Information or counter legal analysis about whether or not CSIS or the RCMP or anyone else should be doing what they're doing.
Whether they should get this particular warrant,
whether they should be allowed to surveil.
So basically they're just deciding amongst themselves whether or not this is good or whether it's not.
And that's a violation of just basic principles of democracy,
let alone there's no transparency in any of that.
And they'll say,
well,
it's for national security purposes.
I refer to national security as the garlic.
You wear it around your neck to keep the vampires away.
If the vampires show up,
you say,
whew,
good thing we have this garlic.
And if the vampires don't show up,
you say,
look,
the garlic's working.
There's endless justification in this kind of conception for more garlic.
Because it's always working.
It's always needed in this paradigm.
Because if you don't see the threat,
that means it's working,
and if you do see the threat,
that means we need it.
How on earth did we come to this sort of logic where there is never enough because one of these two things is operative,
right?
That's what you hear in the rhetoric all the time.
They wanted people to think that to be safe they needed to give up their rights and so they needed to create a terrorist situation and
they thought that we would be good targets for that because we were so new to the religion and so naive.
July 1 is D-Day,
as they started to refer to it,
and that's where we need to get.
And then about a week or so before
July 1,
I want to say it was June 25,
a new lead investigator is brought in underneath the team commander,
whose role was to be the finisher,
to get this across the finish line.
Came out in court that the arrest warrants were to be executed on Canada Day.
I believe it was four months before the actual crime took place.
I was taken before this guy,
Abdulmanan,
who I was told he had flown all the way from Pakistan to meet with us.
An operation,
Mr.
Big,
is a police investigation technique that the police will use when they are convinced that they identified a person who committed a serious crime as a unsolved murder,
but they did not...
They have evidence to accuse him.
So Mr.
Big,
it's an operation during which they will bring the targeted person to make a confession.
It's the same thing that the Sarnoff brothers did.
I wanted to continue their work.
In the case of Project Souvenir,
what they did was they used elements of Mr.
Big.
For example,
when Omar Natal meets the one who is high in the false terrorist organization,
to get Natal to make an incriminating statement,
It means,
yes,
it's my plan,
I want to make the bomb.
What is your,
what is your,
what's your plan?
I don't know.
This is not my idea,
this is his idea.
And I'm like,
oh fuck,
he said Canada Day,
not me.
And I'm like,
oh for fuck's sakes,
you're not ready.
Abdul Qadir,
he said to me,
he said,
why did you tell him that it was my idea?
He needed to hear that it was your idea.
I got you one more chance,
he's going to come in.
And he was on the phone texting.
And this time you better perform.
I was so terrified of what's going to happen if we did not get that C4.
So I'm doing what I can in that moment to stay alive.
When I go running out to him and I plead,
I want to fight.
My wife wants to fight.
We can fight.
Help us.
Please help us.
And so he stands up and said,
Fine.
You'll have your C4.
A lot of these agencies,
for them,
the past is what occurred yesterday.
And they often see the past as not being relevant.
And yet I would argue,
certainly in a Canadian context,
if you want to understand Bill C-51 and some of the changes that were brought in...
You have to know what happened in the
1970s with the disruption operations.
In the 70s you have,
you know,
right after the October crisis,
you have a lot of fear.
That the FLQ is going to do something more.
And there's a lot of fear over how the RCMP is going to properly track people.
How can we stay ahead of this?
How can we know what's happening?
But in their attempts to stay ahead of it,
they create some of it.
They break into a party Quebecois headquarters,
they steal their memberships list,
they copy it,
they break into a small news agency,
steal their files,
they famously burn a barn.
So there was supposedly going to be a meeting between members of the Black Panthers and supposedly FLQ members.
The police wanted to plant a microphone to record it,
but they couldn't,
for technological reasons,
couldn't put the mic in.
And so they actually destroyed the barn.
They actually burned the barn to stop the meeting from taking place.
And then they destroyed almost all of the files as well.
So the reason we know about the things in Quebec is because you had the Keeble inquiry,
you had the MacDonald commission,
where some of this came out.
One of the famous infiltration cases in the 70s is Carole Deveaux,
alias Poupette,
who infiltrated the FLQ for five years.
She participated in organizing a qualified flight.
She participated in an attack on the fire bomb against the company Briggs.
She participated in an extortion attempt with the federal government.
And that's just for this informant from the Montreal Police.
In addition to all this,
at the same time,
the GRC wrote a communique of the FLQ to invite the FLQists to continue the armed struggle after Pierre Vallière said,
no,
I withdraw from all this to go to the
Parti Québécois.
So the police encourages the FLQ to continue in their radicalism.
They worried that the FLQ would infiltrate the Parti Québécois and that it would be harder for the RCMP to monitor them there because the Parti Québécois was legal.
Claude Marin,
who was the number two man in the Parti Québécois government.
Only René Lévesque was above him in the party,
and he was the architect of the whole strategy of the referendum that was held in 1980.
And it turned out that Claude Marin was a paid informant of the RCMP.
They were doing lots of other things outside of Quebec.
They got a lot less attention,
but we,
in a sense,
will never know because they destroyed almost all of the files.
One of the reasons they did this is because they'd seen what had happened in the U.S.
with the FBI's COINTELPRO files becoming public.
Pierre Trudeau,
in one of its very last acts,
in fact,
before going out of office,
passed the Canadian Security Intelligence Service Act,
the CSIS Act,
which,
among other things,
separated the security service out of the RCMP so that you had policing and security intelligence as separate bodies.
And that was one of the ironies,
is that you have
CSIS created in 1984,
largely because of disruption operations carried out by the RCMP,
mainly in Quebec,
but elsewhere,
that went horribly wrong,
inquiries.
And so then you have CSIS created as a result,
and then
Bill C-51 gives CSIS powers to carry out disruption operations of the type that were illegal in the 70s,
but now have the blessing of the state.
The SCRS did not expect the Parliament to give it the authorization to break the law.
In fact,
there are several well-documented cases of SCRS informants who have been given provocation.
There is the case of Marc-André Boivin,
who was a union activist and informant for the SCRS for 15 years and who was sentenced to 15 months in prison for his participation in bomb attacks.
The oppression is just mounting and mounting and mounting and the time to fight is now.
White power There is the case of Grant Bristow,
who is a co-founder of the Heritage Fund,
the white supremacist organization that was the most dangerous.
and the most powerful in Canada in the 90s,
and who led a campaign of disturbance and sabotage against anti-racist activists who mobilized against white supremacists.
He did all this without ever being accused.
And there is also the case of Joseph Gilbrou,
alias Youssef Muammar,
alias Abu Djihad,
who was depicted as a leader of the Muslim community and who sent death threats,
terrorist attacks,
especially against the Montreal metro for years and who was never worried because he was protected by the SCRS.
How many other cases of SCRS informants have acted as provocateur agents that we will never discover because they are protected by the highest authorities?
Okay,
do you see this?
Because Home Depot is just there.
We're gonna go there.
How much,
what do you need now?
Glue,
nails,
a couple more clocks.
Oh,
they didn't have the clocks there?
They were all digital.
They had taken some steps.
They had been involved in the purchase of these materials to eventually build these bombs.
They played a role in their construction over a few days at a hotel out in Tawasin.
It doesn't seem real.
I have that same feeling.
It's surreal.
Yeah,
it's not that it's not...
I feel like I'm in a movie.
I really do.
Now it's really happening,
you know.
Before it was just talk,
it wasn't reality,
you know.
Now
I am stuck with this.
Bill C-51,
one of its extremely problematic innovations,
was to introduce this category of...
activities that undermine the security of Canada as the basis for information sharing exercises between national security agencies.
And within the list of activities that were listed as activities that undermine the security of Canada were things that imperil critical infrastructure,
i.e.
Represented as pipelines,
activities that undermine the sovereignty or imperil the sovereignty of Canada,
Indigenous resistance.
If you protested the Enbridge Northern Gateway Pipeline,
Canada's spy agency may have you on file.
There aren't very many organized environmentalists in Canada who don't think that they're under surveillance or are very,
very concerned about their sort of classification as a national security threat.
There's a reason for that.
I mean,
this has already been established.
in relation to some of the demonstrations that CSIS is interested in them,
that the RCMP are interested in them,
that they're being profiled,
all of these things.
That's very clearly the case.
Questions are currently being raised about the role of Canada's spy agency after British Columbia's Civil Liberties Association released thousands of pages of documents.
The group alleges CSIS monitored the activities of Indigenous groups.
And environmental protesters of the Northern Gateway Pipeline and shared some of the information it collected with oil companies.
BCCLA's files,
the so-called protest papers,
revealed very disturbing evidence of the use of mass surveillance against Indigenous land and water protectors,
surveillance that was shared with the oil industry in the U.S.
We've seen police agencies being hired by extractive corporations to serve effectively as their private enforcement mechanism for their projects of depredations of Indigenous lands.
And so this isn't a hypothetical when we are considering the use of these apparatuses of national security to repress opposition.
to what is in fact the greatest threat to our collective human security,
which is the catastrophe of climate and ecological breakdown,
which we are confronting.
And yet the state continues to prioritize the interests of those who are advancing this apocalypse rather than those who are opposing it.
Climate change is happening faster than we'll be able to deal with in a few years,
like if we don't get a hold of this.
So what do you do when you're a government that actually doesn't care about that,
but only cares about power and wealth in the here and now?
You have to manufacture some reason to maintain the status quo.
So what do you do?
What do they always do?
They manufacture some kind of threat.
Now people who go and march in protective old growth forests or protect water,
they're eco-terrorists.
And even the terminology has changed.
Not environmentalists anymore.
Not conservationists.
You're an eco-
terrorist.
Because if you're a terrorist,
that means we can monitor,
surveil,
criminalize,
do whatever we want to you,
and portray that as a threat to public safety and national security to justify what we're doing to maintain the status quo.
You'll never know the true form of terror until you're holding literal ticking time bomb in your hand.
And to this day,
the sound of a ticking clock sets me and my wife into a state of panic and we're on drugs and treatment for PTSD.
It's too late for that,
Anna.
It took about three days for them to,
in effect,
glue some nails into a pressure cooker.
That was about as far as they could get.
Once their part there was done,
off those devices went to...
what they believed to be the terrorists,
but were of course officers who sort of fixed them up,
put in a tiny bit of C4 along with modeling clay from Michael's to make it look like there was a whole bunch of C4 in there,
and then off they went to Victoria and then they actually planted the devices.
The police provocation benefits the police first and foremost.
It allows us to justify budgets,
to come and say,
look at the terrorist villains we've caught.
That's why we need more power,
that's why we need more ferocious anti-terrorist laws,
while the police were behind all this,
orchestrated everything.
If you can go out and get a successful prosecution on a robbery case,
that's a police car and a cop and some guy doing an investigation.
You have to do wiretap,
you have to do sophisticated surveillance,
data monitoring,
and the related kind of high-tech,
sophisticated policing.
That's money.
That's resources.
That's got to come from somewhere.
And the way you get it there is by having successful prosecutions.
You can't run a case for two years and show nothing for it and think you're going to get a budget the following year.
So I think there's a massive incentive on the part of the enforcement agencies who want to try to upgrade to higher-level equipment to target crimes.
alleged crimes or manufactured crimes to make sure that that budget gets met.
There's huge money involved in the national security industry and tools of policing and everything that you can think of from malware
to drones it's all going into the funnels of policing or national security.
It's a massive massive industry and they have these
astonishing trade shows where you find out you know the tools of the future and what they're planning to empower you to do the old issues of human sources infiltrating and and into groups and so on i think we're
probably going to see less of that and we're going to see a great deal more of scrutiny of the data sphere.
The technological advances in surveillance
And the capacity that now exists to collect and to analyze that so-called big data have the potential for creating these huge databases and increasingly sophisticated algorithms
that can develop profiles of the kind of people that might be radicalized or the kind of people that might pose a threat,
which can be very,
very dangerous.
Even if all of our communications are intercepted,
the consequences differ greatly depending on how we connect to certain variables.
What religious beliefs,
political beliefs,
race,
ethnicity,
sexuality,
and certain groups that have historically been marginalized end up disproportionately experiencing the consequences of that surveillance.
We're heading towards that,
I think,
where people are going to be targeted simply because they fit certain characteristics that a computer program has flagged up.
And then they'll get the really intrusive surveillance coming in after that.
We've come a very long way in a short amount of time in terms of policing powers.
What you could do,
for example,
with the powers that the CSE now has for what are called active cyber,
we can cyber attack you,
right?
We can do things that,
again,
simply didn't exist before.
This is all just like forced on us.
We have no option,
we have no way out,
we have to do it.
We're in Victoria,
choosing a target.
We drove around for like a long time because I didn't have a plan.
The thought came to me,
what if we just blew up a government building?
Then we wouldn't have to hurt anyone.
Would your boss be angry?
Because I promised him a high kill count.
No,
he's not going to be angry.
This is your plan,
he said.
He asked me too,
he said,
do you want maximum damage to this building or to people?
And I said,
to the building,
to the building.
And by the grace of God,
it was accepted as a mission.
He pointed to some bushes and he said,
that's where you're going to plant them.
Stand by,
I have target boarding.
Be wait then.
Okay brother,
let's go pick up the sister.
Open,
open to the sister,
let her in.
Come,
come.
Hide it good.
Yup.
No one's gonna see it.
Not unless they stick their head in there.
You sure?
Yeah.
Okay.
In my mind,
you know,
only a building was going to get destroyed,
and I prayed,
you know,
I just didn't want anyone to get hurt.
Just,
we're going to blow up a government building,
and that's that,
you know.
He's going to come on and say,
we interrupt this program,
but then we're going to do something.
I got a phone call saying that the bombs didn't go off and something went wrong.
What if it goes off during a time when children are there?
I don't want to kill kids.
What if it goes off now?
The kids are there right now.
I knew we were going to the airport,
but I wasn't sure we were going to make it to this airport alive.
Because now that the deed had been done and had been botched,
maybe he wants to kill me and Anna and anyone who might know him and his friends and just move on to the next country and go commit another act of terror or jihad.
I just prayed to
God that...
Something would happen,
anything would happen,
to prevent these bombs from going off.
We stepped out of that hotel room,
and
I immediately had a machine gun pressed up against my head.
I mean,
obviously there was the panic of the guns and everything,
but really in my heart I felt relief because I thought,
well,
if this is happening,
then either they found the bombs and disarmed them or it was all fake and no one's going to be hurt.
We were able to control and ensure that the devices constructed were unable to detonate and cause harm to other individuals.
The two suspects were arrested in Abbotsford yesterday afternoon and the Victoria Canada Day celebrations proceeded without a hitch.
Once the relief faded and I went to court a few times,
it turned to anger that the police had set us up this whole time.
Then eventually to just resignation,
like I was preparing myself to spend the rest of my life in jail.
You know,
someone might be angry but harmless,
and then going to that angry person and saying,
well,
you know what,
don't just be angry.
There's a target.
Here's the equipment.
Encouraging them,
and then when they take that next step,
slap the cuffs on,
you're in court and you're in jail,
and that's chalked up in the media as a successful counterterrorism operation.
Here,
success was clearly viewed as an arrest and moving forward with charges.
There's another way to look at it,
that success would be if you've determined that these folks have no ability to do something,
well,
mission accomplished,
that they aren't going to be doing anything.
Even if you've increased your budgets and done all kinds of things,
and then nothing happens.
Well,
isn't that the goal,
that nothing happens?
Why you need arrests?
to justify or to view your work as a success?
That's a question,
I think,
that needs to be answered.
a question of wanting to start a big operation that will end with arrests and a condemnation that will allow for a promotion,
to start in the hierarchy.
And also,
I think there are probably several policemen who thought more or less secretly that
Kouroudi is notal.
These two people are poor,
they have no means to defend themselves in front of the courts,
and they will simply fall into a crack,
they will be held in prison for 25 years,
and they will be forgotten by everyone.
Contemporary entrapment practices are preying on when they target those precisely who are most mentally vulnerable,
who have been denied services by the state,
to instead...
turn them into scapegoats for state practices of violence.
It is something that our courts have not adequately addressed,
and so the threat of the people who are rendered most vulnerable by the state continuing to be targeted and made into its scapegoats in this way is very much alive.
Before the trial we had made an application to sort of flip the analysis on its head and try to argue entrapment before a guilty verdict and not surprisingly and quite rightly the court said no you have to have your trial but we had in an effort to try to be more efficient tried to expedite it and just
argue the entrapment because that's where this case felt to be decided but short answer they're convicted because they had committed the offenses
I just put all my faith in the entrapment appeal and that hadn't happened yet when the verdicts came down from the jury.
The court of appeal found that there was a reasonable suspicion that the police,
based on largely Mr.
Nuttall's comments,
had a basis to at least start this operation and proceed with it to an extent,
but then found that they,
well...
Their language,
I think,
was pushed and pushed and pushed to get to the result of manufacturing the crime.
And that's where it led to what the court called the travesty of justice.
Not many who followed this case were surprised when B.C.
Supreme Court overruled the conviction,
except perhaps for the RCMP who built the case against them in the first place.
Even after that decision came down,
CSIS agents were still citing it as an example of the dangers of self-radicalization of individuals going online and being immersed in radical ideology themselves,
when in fact it was known that it was not a case of self-radicalization,
but a case of RCMP radicalization.
On the one hand,
The justice system worked.
We were set free.
On the other hand,
we spent over three years in jail.
We were set up by the Canadian security apparatus.
And it could happen to anyone.
Could happen to someone else.
It could be happening to someone right now.
The Souvenir Project was far from being an isolated outburst.
There is a long line of police provocations that go back to the beginning of the Canadian Confederation and unfortunately,
the public,
the citizens,
are very far from having doubted until...
Where are the
Canadian authorities ready to go in the name of our own security?
There is so little data or information about these disruptive practices,
and so the first most fundamental thing is to reverse this informational asymmetry,
which on the one hand produces a great deal of publicity about the threat of Muslim violence or the threat of of indigenous violence and yet allows the state's own violence to hide behind opaque walls.
So our job,
which is a very heavy burden,
is to continue to advocate and research and show the evidence and keep pushing anywhere we can.
So whether it's in protests,
whether it's speaking out in the media about what's happening,
whether it's like educating people,
whether it's on social media,
at the United Nations,
at the Inter-American Commission on Human Rights,
whatever form it takes,
we have to keep pushing until they finally,
they're just...
Too much evidence and too much damage that they say,
listen,
we've got to act on this.
They stack the deck,
manufacturing the threat To build consent,
to spy on dissent Keep their eye on the left,
only lies on their breath They keep wide in the net,
manufacture the threat Here's the thesis,
keep the underhand
whatever they rats for the cheddar security apparatus check the status they got their black list for the left wings raddest military and police staff with fascists like jan 6 they turn their back and collapse shit it's like if that was anarchist and black lives matters they have a row of tanks to blow us all the tatters let's shatter the mist what matters is this the Clock still gon'
tick,
sand droppin'
like shit We runnin'
out of here,
I...
Just a tip.
Police watch list versus indigenous and environmentalists and all who resist this apocalyptic shit.
We on the edge of the cliff.
We on the brink.
So what the hell do you think the people in power doing in the last hour?